Good morning!
（興津(おきつ)）
おはようございます
Good morning!
（一同）
おはようございます
Good morning, everyone.
（丸川(まるかわ)）
はい おはよう
Episode 5 will be delivered today.
（あおい）
本日 ５話納品の予定です
（太郎(たろう)）
放映２週間前
That's two weeks ahead of schedule.
I guess this is standard for Musani now.
まっ これがムサニの
スタンダードでしょうね
Not to mention, part A of
episode 12 is right on track too!
そして 12話Ａパートも
着々進行中　イェイ！
Episode 11's AD and storyboarder Iketani Hiroshi attempted escape for the 17th time.
（矢野(やの)）
11話 コンテ演出の池谷(いけたに)ひろし
通算17回目の逃亡を図りましたが
I managed to stop him, and he will attend the filming meeting at noon.
これを直前で阻止
12時より撮影打ちに入ります
Episode 8's rush check is scheduled for 17:00.
（佐藤(さとう)）
８話のラッシュチェックを
17時より行う予定です
As for episode 13, Andou-san and I are printing the 3D layouts.
13話は安藤(あんどう)さんと一緒に
３Ｄレイアウト出力を行います
Episode 9 will also have a rush check today, at 18:00.
（安藤）
９話 同じく18時より
ラッシュチェックです
I have a meeting in Shinjuku at 14:00.
I'll be back around 23:00.
（渡辺(わたなべ)）
14時より新宿で打ち合わせ
帰りは23時です
I don't really have anything.
（平岡(ひらおか)）
特にありません
玄関のドアを開けっ放しに
しないよう気をつけてください
Please don't leave the front door open.
Leaves and such tend to get blown in.
落ち葉などのゴミが入りますので
It's starting to get chilly,
so be careful not to catch a cold.
だんだんと寒くなってきたからね
風邪をひかないように
Okay.
Understood.
（一同）
はい
We have eight episodes of
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing left to go.
それでは
「第三飛行少女隊」も あと８本
最終話に向かって ロックオン！
Lock on to that final episode!
Sure!
I'll do my best!
Off I go!
（一同）はい
（太郎）太郎 いきま～す！
Noa Wears Undies
（井口(いぐち)）
…にしても監督に こんな
リリカルなところがあるなんて
I had no idea you had such a lyrical side to you, director.
知らなかったな
Are you complimenting me?
（木下(きのした)）
えっ それ褒められてる？
ですよ　珍しく褒めてます
I guess I am, for once!
それで 13話は
井口さんに総作監だけでなく
So could you be episode AD for episode 13,
on top of being chief AD?
各話作監もお願いしたいんです
It is the last episode, and these
storyboards sure pack a punch...
最終話だもんね
しかも木下誠一(せいいち) こん身のコンテ！
（木下）
いや～
Aw, shucks...
But 450 cuts for a single episode might knock us all out.
…つか 全部で450カットって
こん身にも程があるよね
Once I got started, I just couldn't stop.
（木下）
描いてたら
つい止まんなくなってさ
That's so you.
（井口）何が“つい”だか
（木下）すいません
Sorry.
As for episode 13's schedule,
cutting is set for November 11th.
13話のスケジュールなんですが
カッティングは11月11日
I pushed back dubbing as far as possible, to December 14th.
ダビングはギリギリまで引っ張って
12月14日です
That's not a lot of time.
うは～ キツキツだね
大変な状況は
分かっているんですが なんとか
I know it won't be easy,
but this is still our best option.
11話 12話の総作監作業も
だんごで きてるからな
It clashes with the CAD work for episodes 11 and 12 too.
But I'd really love to do it...
やりたいんだけどな～
やっぱ あーし１人じゃ無理だね
頑張っても250かな
Yeah, I won't be able to do this by myself.
I could get up to 250 done at best.
Would you like an assistant?
（あおい）作監補佐 立てますか？
（井口）うん　ヘルプ欲しい
Yeah, some help would be great.
In that case...
そうしたら 小笠原(おがさわら)さんに
お願いしてみようと思いますが
I can ask Ogasawara-san.
（井口）
う～ん 綸子(りんこ)はんなら
Rinko-han could do 120 or so.
120は頼めるか　で… 残り80？
What about the remaining 80?
Well, Ogasawara-san might be able to—
う～んと 小笠原さんにもう少し…
Let's ask Emacchi!
絵麻(えま)っちに
やってもらえないかな？
（あおい）えっ？
（木下）安原(やすはら)さん？
Yasuhara-san?
えっと 安原さんって
原画 何年目だっけ？
How many years has she been working as a keyframer?
Three years.
３年目です
Isn't it a bit too soon?
ちょい早くない？
Rinko-han was doing character designs only two years after she started keyframing.
（井口）
いや～ 綸子はんなんて
原画に上がって２年目には
もうキャラデやってましたよ
あの人は天才だからさ
Well, she's a genius.
Emacchi ain't half bad either.
（井口）
絵麻っちだって いいですよ
She's improved like crazy in the past year with Exodus.
…つうか「えくそだすっ！」から
この１年で
むっちゃ うまくなったっしょ
Remember how well she pulled off Aria's sour plum scene in episode 4?
「サンジョ」４話
ありあが梅干し食べるシーン
うなったもん！
That's true.
（木下）
まあね キャラが食事する
シーンって難しいからね
Animating people eating isn't easy.
I think that scene established Aria as a lovable, awkward girl.
（井口）
あれで ありあの
不器用系いじらしキャラが
伝わった感あるよね！
あと 絵麻っちの絵って
あーしと癖 似てるんで
Also, her style and nuances are similar to mine,
やりやすいってとこもあるかな
so it'd be easy to work with her.
I see.
なるほど　でも 受けてくれるかな
But do you think she'd be up for it?
ちょっと話してみてくれる？
Could you ask her? Thanks.
（木下）うまくね
（井口）ぜひに！
Please!
Sure!
はい！
Assistant AD?
（絵麻）
作監補佐？
Isn't that great, Ema?
よかったね 絵麻
Ema?
絵麻？
Wouldn't I only cause more trouble?
迷惑かけちゃわないかな？
Not at all!
全然　だって井口さんが
“ぜひに”って言ってくれたんだよ
Iguchi-san's the one who suggested you!
But I don't know...
（絵麻）
自信ないな
You'll be fine!
If anyone can do it, it's you!
大丈夫だって！
絵麻ならやれるよ
That's easy for you to say, but it's a whole 80 cuts.
おいちゃんは軽く言うけど―
80カットもあるし
（あおい）あっ…
I'm still working on Mellon's scene from episode 11 too.
11話のウリ坊のカットも まだだし
それは…
Well...
What if it's my fault the last episode looks weird?
最終話で
変な絵になっちゃったら…
I really can't—
（絵麻）やっぱり 断った…
（あおい）待って 絵麻！
Hold on, Ema!
Take time and think this over carefully!
一回よ～く考えて
それから返事聞かせて！
Then give me your answer.
うん　分かった
Okay. I will.
If Ema refuses, Ogasawara-san will have a heavier workload.
（あおい）
もし絵麻が断ったら
小笠原さんに もう少し…
Should I move Segawa-san to episode 13?
瀬川(せがわ)さんをいっそ13話に…
But then...
ああ でも それって…
No, that wouldn't work.
やっぱりダメだ
Ninety percent of production's problems are organizing staff.
（ミムジー）
制作の悩みの９割は
人間関係だよね
Life's tough, that's for sure.
せちがらい せちがらい
Their job is to get everyone working together, so that's just how it is.
（ロロ）
スタッフをつなぐ仕事だから
どうしても そうなっちゃうよね
I bet they'd rather worry about bigger problems.
どうせなら
もっと大きなことで悩みたいよね
Like global warming or world peace.
環境問題とか世界平和とかさ
Those are crazy big!
大きすぎるよ！
I know how you must feel about this.
瀬川さんのお気持ちもあると
思いますが
So it's safe to assume that you'll take responsibility if something happens?
（瀬川）
それって この次 何かあったら
宮森(みやもり)さんが
責任取ってくれるってことで
いいんだよね？
Ye... Yes!
えっ… はい！
So tell me, how exactly will you do that?
具体的にはどうやって？
Do you understand what it means to be listed as AD in the credits?
エンドクレジットに
作監の名前が出る意味 分かる？
Good or bad, it's all on my shoulders.
いいものも悪いものも
全部こっちの責任になるんだよ
I do understand.
分かります！
立場は違いますが私も一緒です！
I might have a different role, but it's the same for me.
Sort of...
…と思います
I think your dissatisfaction with Hiraoka comes from the keyframers he gathered.
瀬川さんの
平岡への不信感の第１は
平岡が集めてきた
原画マンへのものだと思います
So if you say a keyframer is no good,
we won't use them.
ですから 瀬川さんが
“ない”と判断した原画マンは
入れません！
He won't just make you handle retakes by yourself either.
そして リテークを
無責任に瀬川さんに丸投げするのは
なしにします！
He'll bring you the finished keyframes every day,
あと 上がった原画は
毎日お届けします
not in huge batches here and there.
ためてお渡しして
一気に上げてくれとか
And no more impossible requests like "Do them all at once."
ムチャなお願いは絶対しません！
新しく仕事を振る
アニメーターさんの名前も
Give me the names of the
animators you plan on adding.
事前に教えて
Also, send me a status report every day.
あと 状況表は
必ず毎日送ってください
Of course! Thank you very much!
はい もちろんです！
ありがとうございます！
あ～ もう！
Well, shoot.
I intended to refuse.
ホントは断ろうと思ってたんだ
Once there's trouble with a job, I lose motivation.
一回 ケチついた仕事は
モチベーション下がるしね
But...
（瀬川）
でも
you managed to convince me.
宮森さんにほだされた
For creators, each and every episode becomes a part of their portfolio.
だから覚えておいて
クリエーターには関わった話数
一本一本が名刺代わりってこと
There's no such thing as "just another show."
流して描く作品なんてないってこと
Got it!
はい！
絵麻先輩！
Ema-senpai?
（絵麻）りーちゃん 仕事中？
（みどり）…っす！
Rii-chan, are you busy?
Yep.
I'm working on the storyboards to order the VA script.
アフレコ台本発注用の
絵コンテを作ってるとこです
For the last episode.
（みどり）最終話の
（絵麻）発注用の絵コンテ？
Order the script?
I get rid of notices unrelated to sound, like "stick pan" or "on the ones,"
こういう
“付けパン”の“付け”とか
“１コマ打ち”とか
音響に関係ないト書きは削って
and leave stuff like "Aria close-up" or "Noa moves her shoulder."
“ありあアップ”とか
“ノア 肩すくめる”とか
I even add information necessary for sound editing.
音響さんに必要な情報だけ残したり
修正して書き入れたりって感じで
へえ～ すごいね りーちゃん
That's amazing.
I heard they usually skip this step these days,
（みどり）
こういう作業は最近
どこもあんまりやってないって
聞いたっすけど
but I've gotten a brand new perspective of the scenario by working on this!
これ任せてもらえて
シナリオの読み方が
また変わったですよ
Perspective?
（絵麻）読み方？
（みどり）うん！
Yup!
After all, everyone does storyboards differently.
やっぱ絵コンテって
100人100通りなんすよね
Homeless Beebee
I read Beebee and Shirobeko,
「パッチ」とか「白べこ」とか
読ませてもらったら
今と全然テンポ感が違って
but the pacing in this one is so different.
And yet, it still has the depth.
でも深いな～と思うとこもあって
今 自分の中に
栄養が むくむく入ってきてる気分
I feel like a sponge, soaking up everything thrown at me!
It's lots of fun!
面白いっす！
It makes me nervous to think the VAs are going to act out what I write!
自分の一文に合わせて
声優さんが演技するかと思うと
超ビビるっす！
Yeah, it does make you nervous.
うん… ビビるよね
ビビるっす　でも楽しいっていうか
It so does! But it's still totally fun!
I just wanna scream with joy!
なんかホントに
“ひゃ～”って感じで
With joy? Not shaking with fear?
“ひゃ～”？
（絵麻）“ブルブル”じゃなくて？
（みどり）“ひゃ～”っすよ！
Yup, with joy!
If you told me a year ago that I'd be working on
an anime, I would've told you to dream on!
だって去年の今頃なんて
自分が
アニメの制作に関われるなんて
夢にも思ってなかったんすから
It doesn't scare you, Rii-chan?
（絵麻）
りーちゃんは怖くないんだね
What do you mean, Ema-senpai?
何言ってんすか 絵麻先輩
All I'm scared of is not becoming a scriptwriter!
怖いのは脚本家になれないことです
Shutting down
（平岡）
う～っす
I'm off.
You're leaving, Dai-chan?
（太郎）あれっ 大(だい)ちゃん帰るの？
（平岡）帰るけど
I am.
I'll go with you, then.
じゃあ俺も帰る
太郎　お前 夜便の手配は？
Tarou, what about the late night packs?
完了っす！
俺を誰だと思ってるんすか？
They're done! Who do you think I am?
It's time for some man time! Stay inside, kids!
これからは大人の時間っすよ
子供は ちゃいちゃい
Let's go, Dai-chan!
行こうぜ 大ちゃ～ん！
We don't get off this early every day, you know.
Let's grab something to eat! I know just the place!
せっかくこんな時間に帰れるんだし
一緒に飯でも行っちゃう？　俺の…
See you later!
（安藤･佐藤）お疲れさまでした
（矢野）あっ
みゃーもり 12話どうなった？
Miyamori, what happened to episode 12?
Segawa-san agreed to do it in the end.
なんとか瀬川さんに
オーケーしてもらいました
That's great.
よかったじゃん！
One less thing to worry about.
これで ちょっと一安心です
（安藤）うん？
（矢野）一度 失った信用は
It's nearly impossible to restore lost trust.
なかなか元には戻らないって話
How so? That sounded pretty dark.
（佐藤）えっ なんですか？　怖い
（矢野）監督がそうでしょ
Just think about the director.
Everything you've built up could collapse in a second.
積み上げてきたものが
崩れるのは一瞬
Don't take the trust of others for granted.
“いつまでも あると思うな
他人の信用”だよ
I'll remember that!
肝に銘じます！
But it's not impossible to restore it either!
でも 絶対 元に戻せないって
わけじゃないですから　うん
（携帯電話のバイブ音）
ん？　っと…
Oh...
Mii-chan
Incoming Call
Oden
Is it okay for you to leave You-chan home alone?
（新川(しんかわ)）
洋(よう)ちゃん １人にしといて
大丈夫なの？
（堂本(どうもと)）
うん 大丈夫 大丈夫
もう中学生だし
He'll be fine. He's already in junior high.
Wow, is he really?
Oden
（新川）
マジ？
もうそんな大っきくなったの
（堂本）
背 伸びてホント邪魔
一食で２合食べるからね
And already a pain to feed.
He eats two servings of rice a meal.
（新川）
２合！
お母さん大変だね 稼がないと
Two?!
Being a mom sounds tough and expensive.
ホントだよ
Tell me about it.
To top it off, he started saying how he wants to work in the industry too.
おまけに最近 アニメの仕事
やりたいとか言いだしてさ
Could this get any worse?
頭 痛いわ
それは やめさしたほうがいいわ
普通のサラリーマンが一番だって
You should make him give up on that.
A normal office job would be for the best.
Huh? Didn't you say you liked Nick Cage?
えっ？　あなたニコケイがいいって
言ってたじゃない
He's the opposite of an office drone.
サラリーマンとは真逆でしょ
I'm into Edgar Ramirez now.
（新川）今はエドガー･ラミレス
（堂本）誰それ？
Who's that?
A super-hot Latino actor.
ラテン系のイケメン俳優
You really like cleft chins, don't you?
What's with that?
ホント 顎割れてる系好きだよね
どうなの それ？
You don't see any around here.
だって周りにいないんだもん
顎割れてる系っていうか 男が
Not just cleft-chinned men, but real men in general.
Well, you're right about that.
男いないね
Make sure You-chan grows up to be a great guy, okay?
洋ちゃん いい男に育ててよ
Not sure if I can.
どうだろ
He spends his entire allowance on LNs at this point.
あいつ 今 お小遣い全部
ラノベに費やしてるからね
（新川）
うひゃ～！
The other day he asked me why I don't work for Naniwa Animation.
（堂本）
“お母さん
なにわアニメーションの―”
“仕事しないの？”
なんて聞かれた日にゃ もうね
I was just like...
くるね～ くる くる！
I know what you mean.
But if he really wants to do it, then I won't stop him.
でもね
ホントにやりたいっつうんなら
止められないしね
Yeah.
まあね
What was that saying?
"The sins of the parents fall on the child"?
こういうの なんつうんだっけ
“親の因果が子に報い”？
You mean, "He's just a chip off the old block."
違う違う
“カエルの子はカエル”
Yeah, that's it!
それだ！
Wouldn't want it to fall on him.
（新川）報いちゃダメでしょ
（堂本）ウフフフ…
Will my Youji end up like Tarou or Hiraoka?
洋司(ようじ) あいつ
太郎とか平岡みたいになるのかな
We have to do everything we can
to make sure he doesn't!
それは全力で阻止しようよ！
You can get whatever you'd like! My treat!
（太郎）
今日はおごり　好きなの頼んでよ！
We're buddies! You know, buddies!
俺たちゃバディだから バディ！
It means we're partners!
分かる？　相棒って意味！
はいはい 俺たちの固い絆に
かんぱ～い！
Cheers to our powerful bond of friendship!
（平岡）
乾杯
Cheers.
The PAs don't coordinate the work
they do on different episodes at all.
（新川）
…つうか 連携が取れてないんだよ
各話の制作がさ
They only care about their own episodes.
自分の話数のことしか
考えてないんだよね
That's true.
ああ それはそう
They prioritize their part whenever they discuss things. It's not easy.
それで自分の話数優先で
もの言ってくるから ちょっとね
動検通してって言ってるのに
なかなか通らないし
I tell them to pass stuff to
tween check, but it takes ages.
リテーク多すぎるし
その日のうちに戻せって言うし
Retakes all over the place,
and they still want it done same day.
打ち合わせの連絡は
せめて３日前にしてほしいよね
I wish they'd tell me about meetings at least three days in advance.
前日に連絡とか無理だから！
Can't just squeeze it in on one day's notice!
They only tell me when to finish, but not how much work to do.
アップ日だけ知らされて
作業量が分からないって
Isn't that bullying, in a way?
それ どんな罰ゲームって感じ
I feel you.
ホント
At least Miyamori-san's trying.
（堂本）
まあ 宮森さんは
頑張ってるほうだと思うけどね
What do you think about the schedule
Princess Aoi made for the last two episodes?
（新川）
どうもっさん どう思う？
あおい嬢による
ラスト２本のスケジュール
Ah, that? A naive dream.
（堂本）
まあ～ あれはね 夢
夢で悪けりゃ 願望
She's in for a rude awakening.
You said it.
（新川）
だよね～
Koganei Animation said they could help a bit, so I thought I should book them in advance.
小金井(こがねい)動画が ちょっとだけなら
手伝えるって言ってたから
今から押さえとこうかと思って
さすが！
Good call!
But don't tell Princess Aoi just yet.
Production would slack off if they knew.
ああ でも まだ あおい嬢には
言わないほうがいいかも
絶対その下で
気ぃ抜くヤツが出てくるから
You mean Tarou? Or Tarou? Or maybe Tarou?
（堂本）
太郎とか 太郎とか 太郎とかね
You forgot Hiraoka.
（新川）あと平岡
（堂本）ああ～
Let them live off bread and water.
（新川）
あいつらなんか ちくわぶでも
食わせとけばいいんだよ
（堂本）
そうだ そうだ！
牛スジは我らのもんだ！
That just means more of this feast for us!
（堂本･新川）
かんぱ～い！
Cheers!
ぷは～！
This might be our last night out like this.
…っていうか
今日が最後の晩さんかもね
It's gonna be hell for a while.
しばらく地獄だね
I'll have some sake.
Also, three sticks of beef tendon.
（堂本）
日本酒 飲んじゃおっかな
あと牛スジ３本
I'll have plum sour.
（新川）
私 バイスサワー
These two are the voice actors of the future!
（テレビ:女性ＭＣ）
未来に羽ばたく
アイドル声優のお二人です！
Good evening!
Special
Voice Actor
Newbie
（かな･声優）
こんばんは～！
You're both so cute!
（男性ＭＣ）
いや～
２人とも かわいいですね～！
（かな）エヘヘ…
（声優）ありがとうございます
Thank you!
Kana-chan, I heard you're still in high school. Is that true?
（男性ＭＣ）
しかも かなちゃんは
現役女子高生！
（かな）
そうなんです～
It is!
Have you had problems with the job so far?
（女性ＭＣ）
何か今までで困ったことって
ありますか？
I love traveling, but it's hard for me to make personal plans.
（かな）
私 旅行が好きなんですけど
予定が立てられないんですよ
急に収録日が変わったりするんで
Recording dates can change so suddenly.
I see! It's a tough line of work for sure!
（男性ＭＣ）なるほど～
（しずか）じゃあ代わったげようか
Mind passing some of that problem to me?
And when recordings overlap with my exams, it can be pretty tough.
（かな）
あとテストの時と仕事が重なると
やっぱりちょっと大変
代わる代わる
I'd gladly switch with you.
I always make sure to take care of myself, you know!
（声優）
私は体調管理に気を配ってます
レギュラー４本に加えて…
I keep it to four weeklies, and—
Master! Another beer for me!
お兄さん ビールお代わり！
You're always having so much fun.
お前って いつも楽しそうだな
I ain't having fun. I'm suffering, actually.
俺は楽しくなんかない
むしろ つらい！
I'm walking the thorny path towards my dream!
なぜなら 野望に向かって
一歩一歩 進んでいるところだから
Are you retarded? Well, dream on!
バカじゃねえの　野望とか
What are you saying? A man without a dream is no—
何言ってんの！
男子たるもの 野望 大事…
Shut up already. You're annoying.
やめろよ ウゼえな
That's right! That Miyamori's really annoying!
そう！　そうなのよ
ウゼえのよ 宮森 あいつ
She's acting all high and mighty just because she's PM now,
（太郎）
今はデスクだなんだって
でっかい顔してっけどさ
but next year it's gonna be someone else!
来年になったら立場逆転だから！
I'm making director!
（太郎）俺 監督だからさ
（平岡）いや 無理だろ
Yeah, right.
You're such a buzzkill, Dai-chan.
もう 大ちゃん つまんない男だね
そんなこと言ってたら
プロデューサーにしてあげないよ
I won't make you producer if you act like that.
（平岡）なりたかねえよ！
（太郎）なりなさい
I don't want to be producer.
You should!
（平岡）なんでだよ
（太郎）なるの！
Why?
You will!
A producer only finds and looks after the staff, that's all.
Ｐなんて結局 スタッフを
締め上げるだけの役職だろ
Really?
そうなの？
（太郎）ああ…
（平岡）兄さん ハイボール！
A highball for me!
I gave up dreaming about what I want to achieve or become ages ago.
（平岡）
なんになりてえとか
何やりてえとか
んなもん とっくに捨てたよ
Thanks!
（太郎）
えっ とっくにってことは
前はあったの？
Thank you! Please come again!
So that means you used to dream big?
What?
何？
Come on, tell me about it.
何よ～ なんなのよ？
In a shitty place, shitty people can only make shit. No surprises.
（平岡）
クソみたいなところだったよ
クソみたいなヤツらが
クソみてえなもんしか作れねえのは
当たり前だっつうの
（玄関のチャイム）
（平岡）なのに俺１人 間に入って
But they put me in between,
where I was always apologizing to everyone,
あっちに謝り こっちに謝り
さんざん間 取り持って調整して
and when I finally sorted things out between them...
I promise it'll be great when it's done!
上がれば絶対
いいものになりますから！
大丈夫ですから！
It'll be fine!
（制作デスク）
だったら回収するまで
帰ってくんじゃねえよ！
Then don't come back until you got something!
You bum me out, man.
I can't get anything done like this.
（アニメーター）
暗いんだよ お前
上がるもんも上がんねえよ
He said it'll be done tomorrow.
あしたには上がるそうですから
He's just blowing you off.
If this fails, can you take responsibility?
（制作デスク）
ナメられてんだよ！
落としたら
お前が責任取れんのかよ！
Is this really finished?
（平岡）
これで完成ですか？
（アニメーター）
お前が上げろっつったんだろ
持ってけよ
You're the one who said to just do it already.
Take it or leave it.
No can do. Cancel it.
（演出家）
やっぱ無理　引き上げて
But you said you'd—
そんな！
請けていただけるって…
（演出家）
悪い 他の仕事取っちゃった
Sorry, I took another job.
But—
（制作スタッフ１）
もっと身の丈に合った仕事しろ
I took a job from a different place.
Don't demand quality if you don't pay me!
（アニメーター）
クソ安い単価でクオリティーとか
言ってんじゃねえよ
（制作スタッフ２）
怖いよ　電話かけすぎ
Stop it. Why do you keep calling?
（制作デスク）
お前 空回りしてんの気付いてる？
Haven't you realized you're achieving nothing?
Getting stuff done is all that matters.
（平岡）
アニメなんて上がりゃいいんだよ
I was a fool not to understand that.
んなことも分かんねえで
あん時の俺はバカか
バカか 俺は
I must be stupid.
You're not stupid, Dai-chan!
（太郎）
大ちゃんはバカじゃないよ！
It must've been hard...
It must've been really hard, Dai-chan.
つらかったね…
偉かったね 大ちゃん 頑張ったね！
You did what you could.
Oh, stop.
別に
俺 どうせ これ終わったら辞める
I'm quitting once this is done.
ダメ～！　それはダメ！
No! No, you're not!
Why not?
なんでだよ
Because you're my buddy!
We're gonna take the world by storm!
大ちゃんは
俺と世界を取るバディだから！
Award certificate!
（太郎）
表彰状！　平岡大輔(だいすけ)殿！
Sir Hiraoka Daisuke!
貴殿の努力に敬意を表しまして
To honor your astonishing efforts,
ここに わたくし高梨(たかなし)太郎が
表彰いたします！
I, Takanashi Tarou,
hereby present you with this award!
（美沙(みさ)）うわ～！
（あおい）みーちゃん こっち
This way, Mii-chan!
Excuse me!
（美沙）お邪魔します！
（絵麻）いらっしゃい
Come on in!
Wow, this is so different from our studio!
へえ～！
やっぱり うちと全然違う！
Is it really?
そうかな？
Is this a pro's peg bar?
（美沙）
ほお～！
これがプロのタップですか
It's so thin and black! This is so cool!
薄い！　黒い！　カッコいい！
Tablets are cooler, I think.
タブレットのほうがカッコいいよ
I've gotta go back to work.
じゃあ 私 戻ってるから
（絵麻）うん
（美沙）ちっす！
Later!
エヘッ 騒いでちゃいけませんね
仕事 仕事！
I'm not here to fool around, either.
Let's get down to work!
Remember how we went to the theme park?
（美沙）
この間 遊園地
行ったじゃないですか
Yeah.
I can't get the movements to feel as dynamic.
（美沙）
なんか 動きが
ピリッとしないんですよ
（絵麻）
う～ん 原画かな
Keyframes...
Keyframes?
（美沙）原画？
（絵麻）それから中割り
And tweens.
The computer tweens
CG animation automatically, right?
３Ｄってコンピューターが
自動で中割りをしてくれるでしょ
それって多分 等間隔だと思うのね
I think it divides the movement equally between the frames.
But when we draw by hand, we emphasize the important frames, the keyframes.
でも私たちアニメーターは
目に残したい絵
キーになる絵を原画に描くから
Is that like pacing, or adding breakpoints?
メリハリってか
ポイントをつけるってことですかね
多分
テンポやパースが正確すぎると
Kind of.
If the pacing and the angle is too perfect,
it just won't be exciting at all.
逆に快感が湧かないんじゃないかな
Exciting...
快感か
時間と絵の誇張みたいな
It's like, exaggerating both time and the drawings.
Pacing... Angle...
Take a look at this.
Time... Drawings...
（絵麻）これ見てみて
（久乃木(くのぎ)）時間 誇張…
So I should raise this motion curve,
and lower this one?
（美沙）
…とすると
ここの運動曲線を上げて
こちらを戻す… と
（絵麻）
うん あと中割りの絵を
And how about squeezing the motion at the beginning?
もっと始まりのほうに
ためてみたら？
I get it!
（美沙）
なるほどです！
奥行き感を強調するんですね
That emphasizes the distance.
（絵麻）
あっ うん　いい感じ！
Yeah, that looks good!
I kept thinking about only the CG stuff, like texture details.
なんか３Ｄのっていうか
質感とかディテールとか
そういうことばっかり
考えてたんです
But in the end, it's all about the animation!
やっぱり
３Ｄもアニメなんですよね
Thank you so much, Ema-senpai!
ありがとうございます 絵麻先輩！
えっ 私は何も…
But I didn't—
It was really eye-opening!
目の前がパーって
開けた気がします！
Skip
Street
Dai-chan!
（太郎）
大ちゃん！
もっけん行こう もっけん
Let's go find another place!
And plan how to overthrow Miyamori Aoi!
宮森あおい 打倒計画だ！
小せえよ！　俺の野望はな
You're thinking too small!
You know, my dream was
to make the first anime ever
アニメで初めて カンヌで
ある視点部門の作品賞と
to get the Cannes award in a major category and an international critics' award!
国際批評家連盟賞を
取るつもりだったんだよ！
So stupid! I was so stupid!
バ～カ！　俺のバ～カ！
You're not stupid!
大ちゃんはバカじゃない！
Let's go and conquer the seaside capital of animation!
こうなったらアニメーション熱海(あたみ)
取りに行くぞ！　お～！
I'm going home. Kemeko's coming.
帰る　ケメコが来るから
Why?
（しずか）
なんでだよ…
Morning, Emacchi!
（井口）
おはよう 絵麻っち
Good morning!
（絵麻）おはようございます
（井口）うん？
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
Animation Retake
Add small action to Aria showing she noticed the footsteps
Yasuhara
Inagoshi
Segawa
Dou
Hiraoka
（平岡）お疲れさまです
（絵麻）あっ
Morning...
Please take care of that episode 7 retake.
７話リテーク
よろしくお願いします
Segawa-san would like you to add an extra action to match the sound.
瀬川さんから
音に合わせてワンアクション
足してくれってことです
Okay.
（絵麻）
あっ はい
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
Add small action to Aria showing she noticed the footsteps
Yasuhara-san, could you handle this?
Thank you
Animation Retake
Timing Take
Subject
Details
ED
AD
CAD
Color Setting
Tween Check
Cell Check
Filming
ああ… やっぱり
まだ作監なんて無理
I really can't be an AD just yet.
You should do it.
（杉江(すぎえ)）受けたほうがいい
（絵麻）えっ
僕は才能っていうのは 何よりまず
I think that talent is the ability to take chances, and the calm to learn from your mistakes.
チャンスをつかむ握力と
失敗から学べる冷静さだと思う
Drawing skill is second to that.
絵のうまい下手は その次だ
I've seen plenty others with much more skill
僕は僕よりうまい人間が
miss great opportunities because of extreme self-consciousness
僅かな自意識過剰や
つまらない遠慮のせいで
or some mistaken sense of discretion.
チャンスと取りこぼしてきたのを
何度も見た
It's such a shame. I still think about them.
惜しいと思うよ いまだにね
I was just lucky.
僕は運がよかった
I'll do it.
やってみます！
Now's the time to work hard.
（杉江）
今が頑張り時だよ
Yes.
はい！
I'll do my best not to cause trouble for you!
なるべく
ご迷惑をおかけしないよう
頑張ります！
And I'm sure I'll cause trouble for you,
but please put up with it.
ご迷惑をおかけしますが
よろしくお願いします
It might sound funny coming from me,
but there are things you can only learn by trying.
あのね 私が言うのも変だけど
やんないと
分かんないこともあるから
AD work is totally different from just keyframing.
やっぱりね 作監って
原画とは全然違うんだよね
Both what you do and what you learn from it.
やることも 身につくことも
（絵麻）全然？
（井口）うん
It is?
Yeah.
ラッシュチェックで
原画リテークを直すのは作監だから
ADs fix the keyframe retakes from the rush checks,
so you learn what kind of keyframes require retakes.
どういう原画がリテークになるか
分かるようになる
If you can spot retakes,
you can tell a good keyframe.
リテークが見えれば
いい原画が見える
And recognize a bad one too.
悪い原画も分かる
And you start thinking not about individual cuts,
but about scenes, and later whole episodes.
そして
カット単位じゃなくてシーン全体
やがては話数全体で絵が見えてくる
That's when you learn how to give it depth.
そうするとね　芝居が深くなる
And there's plenty of depth!
奥が深いよ　怖いよ
It's scary.
でも だから楽しいんだけどね
But that's what makes it fun!
May I see as well?
（杉江）僕にも見せてくれる？
（絵麻）あっ はい
O-Of course.
Is there something wrong?
何か変ですか？
No.
（杉江）
いや
I couldn't draw this.
これは僕には描けないな
This is something only you could draw.
安原さんにしか描けない絵だ
It's great.
いいね
Thank you very much!
（絵麻）ありがとうございます！
（携帯電話のバイブ音）
3rd Wing Episode 13 Animator Meeting
If you can, come to the next animeet by yourself next time.
あと できれば次は１人で来てね
Is this...
（久乃木）これは…
（一同）あっ！
（一同）
これは？
Is this?
Is this underwear?!
これは 下着ですか？
はい！　これは下着です！
Yes, it is underwear!
（山田(やまだ)）
ノアの下着です！
It is Noa's underwear!
It is white!
（円(まどか)）
それは白いです！
We got your present.
（絵麻の母）
届いたよ 湯飲み
いいの？　あんな高そうな物を
Can you really afford something like this?
Don't worry about that. Happy anniversary!
（絵麻）
いいの　結婚記念日おめでとう
これまで何もしないでごめんね
Sorry I couldn't do anything for you before.
Thank you.
（母）
ありがとう　お父さんと２人で
大事に使わせてもらうね
Your father and I are going to treasure these.
I need to go to work soon.
もう会社に行く時間だね
夜だと 絵麻 いつ仕事終わるか
分からないから 朝 電話したの
I have no idea how late you work at night,
so I called in the morning.
Sorry, gotta go. Bye!
ごめんね　切るね
Wait, Mom!
あのね お母さん
I think I can make a living as an animator.
私 アニメーターで
食べていけると思う
So please, don't worry about me anymore.
だから もう心配しないで
The sky... It's blue.
（鈴木(すずき)）
空って青かったんだ
Noa
Huh?
Aria
I had no idea the sky was this blue.
（鈴木）
私 知らなかった
こんなに空が青くて
That it was this wide!
広いなんてこと！
I think that was it.
（稲浪(いななみ)）
はい こちらオーケーです
何かありますか？
Any concerns?
May I try that last part once more?
あの すみません
最後のとこ もう一回お願いします
I made a mistake.
失敗しちゃいました
No, that was the keeper.
（稲浪）
いや 今の頂きます
Everyone agreed that it fit Aria.
（稲浪）
“これが ありあだよ”って
みんなで言ってたんだよ
よかったよ
You did well.
そんな…
But...
（稲浪）
これで「第三飛行少女隊」
全13本の収録
That marks the end of voice recording for all 13 episodes of 3rd Girls' Fighter Wing.
終了となります　お疲れさまでした
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you very much!
（木下）
お疲れさまでした
鈴木さんのおかげで
本当にいい作品になりました
It turned out great thanks to you, Suzuki-san!
Thank you! Thank you for putting up with me.
ありがとうございます
私 皆さんに
ご迷惑かけてばかりで
（葛城(かつらぎ)）
うんうん　よかった
I'm so glad!
Nighhawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
Incoming Call
Nighthawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
Incoming Call
Nighthawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
Incoming Call
Nighthawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
Incoming Call
Nighthawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
Incoming Call
Nighthawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
Incoming Call
Nighthawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
Incoming Call
Nighthawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
Incoming Call
Nighthawk Publishing
Chazawa Shinsuke
（葛城）
えっ 野亀(のがめ)先生怒ってる？
What?! Nogame-sensei is upset?!
Furious?!
激怒り？
He scrapped all the storyboards for episode 13?!
最終話 絵コンテ 全ボツ？
Hello, this is Musani.
Honda-san, you bringing us something again?
Not that I mind, but watch out or the director will gain another 10 kilos.
Flip the Table
Next time on Shirobako: "Flip the Table 2."
（太郎）
はい ムサニで～す
あっ 本田(ほんだ)さん
また差し入れっすか？
俺はいいんすけど
ほどほどにしないと
監督 10キロ太ってますよ
次回
「ＳＨＩＲＯＢＡＫＯ(シロバコ)」